Wait here for a moment, Damian.
なんば
ひびと
(南波日々人)《ちょっと ここで
待ってろよ ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ》
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#41 Eighty Minutes to Live
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)ハァ…ハァ…｡
H-Hibito...
《ヒ…ヒビト！》
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)お おい…ヒビト！
H-Hey!
Hibito...
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)まだか カレン｡
Ready yet, Karen?
(ｶﾚﾝ)あと３０分はかかるわ｡➡
Not for another thirty minutes.
まだ 往復分の電力しか
準備できてないの｡➡
It only has enough juice to make it there and back.
予備電力として
最低でも今の倍は必要よ｡
To be safe, you'll need twice that amount.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)了解｡
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)≪フレディ≫
Roger that.
Freddy...
関係あるかは わからんが
ヒビトは➡
I don't know if it's related, but Hibito said he saw a flash coming from that area.
光るモノを見たと言っていたんだ｡
ふきん
あの付近で｡
フゥ…｡
What's this, Buddy?
なんだ バディ｡
ユーフォー
またＵＦＯの話か？
More UFO talk?
No, I don't think it's related...
いや 関係ないとは思うぜ｡
関係ないとは思うんだが…｡
I don't think it's important,
マーキュリー６号の
ジョン･グレンに始まり➡
but Mercury 6's John Glenn,
as well as the crews of Apollo 8, 11, 12, and 15,
アポロ計画じゃ ８･１１･１２･
１５･１７号のクルーが➡
all reported something glowing.
はっこうぶったい
み～んな発光物体を見てるんだ｡
なぞ
そんな謎の光を見た付近で
ギブソンが消えて➡
And now, after that flash,
Gibson is missing, along with two crew members.
２人も消えたんだ｡
もしかしたら 何か関係が…｡➡
There might be a connection.
いや 関係ないとは思いつつ…｡
Well, I know it probably isn't related...
There is no connection.
関係ないだろうな それは｡
That's what I thought.
俺も そう思ってた！
全く関係ないぜ｡
There's no connection.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)落ち着けよ バディ…
ここは月だぞ｡
Calm down, Buddy.
We're on the moon.
俺達のジャマをする者なんて
最初からいない｡
There's nothing here that will interfere with our mission.
しょくん
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)諸君｡
Gentlemen...
What can we do for Damian and Hibito?
我々がヒビトとダミアンに
してやれること…｡
きも
めい
だいぜんてい
まず 肝に銘ずべき大前提として➡
First, we must operate under the assumption
that they will both return alive.
２人とも必ず生きて帰ると
信じること｡その上で➡
With that in mind, we must consider our current circumstances,
現在 ２人に起こっているであろう
すいそく
状況を推測し➡
じたい
あらゆる事態を想定した
きゅうじょ
救助体制を整えておくこと｡
and prepare rescue operations for every possible situation.
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)大事なのは 決して事態を
甘く見積もらないことだ｡➡
It is critical that we not treat their predicament lightly.
通信不可で状況が分からない今➡
Given our limited information,
起こりうる最悪のケースを
想定して考えてくれ｡
we must assume a worst case scenario.
(職員)だったら バギーはもう
動かないと考えた方がいい｡
We should assume that the buggy can't be used.
They aren't able to communicate with each other.
(職員)２人とも
通信できていないはずだよ｡
It's possible that they've been separated.
(職員)なら２人は
会えていないかもしれない｡
Their spacesuits may have been damaged.
はそん
(職員)宇宙服の破損も考えられる｡
(職員)ケガをしているとしたら…｡
If they're injured,
there may be sustained bleeding.
(職員)今現在 出血が進んでる
可能性もあるな｡
あずま
(吾妻)クラウドさん｡➡
Claude,
there's something I'd like you to do to eliminate the worst case scenario.
最悪のケースを
最悪でなくするために➡
今すぐ やってほしいことが
あります｡
なんだ？アズマ｡
What's that, Azuma?
While we wait for the Beetle to fully charge,
じゅうでん
(吾妻)ビートルの充電完了を
待っている間に➡
今すぐ動かせる無人ローバーを➡
we should send every available unmanned rover to the site, via remote control.
えんかく　そうさ
遠隔操作で現地へ
向かわせてください｡
(職員)というと？
まずは➡
What do you mean?
Start with all unmanned probes besides Gibson.
たんさ
ギブソン以外の無人探査機を｡➡
それから 酸素生成ローバーの
ブライアン｡➡
And then the oxygen generation system Brian.
The sand digger Spider can also be dispatched.
砂かけマシン
スパイダーでもいい｡
何がどう役に立つか
わからないんだ｡
I can't say for sure how useful they'll prove,
そん
送っておいて損はない｡
but it can't hurt to send them.
確かにな｡
You're right.
ブライアンは全機 走行可能です｡
All Brian units are ready to go.
現地の一番近くにある
３号機を向かわせます｡➡
I'll send #03, the closest unit.
探査機だと
フェンダーがありますが➡
The probe Fender is available, but it's too far away.
現地には ちょっと遠すぎます｡
あとスパイダーですが…➡
As for Spider,
本ミッションでの役割は終えて
停止状態です｡
it completed its job for this mission, so it's in hibernation.
すでに充電を行っている
ビートルの方が早く発進できます｡
Beetle is already charging, so it'll be ready sooner.
Roger that.
了解｡ブライアン３号に
たど
２人のバギーのわだちを辿らせる｡
Have Brian #03 follow their buggy's route.
はんだん
アズマの判断は正しかったな｡➡
Azuma made the right call.
フレディ達が着く前に
しにん
現場をカメラで視認できる｡
We'll have a camera on site before Freddy and Buddy can arrive.
《ヒビト…はっ！》
Hibito...
《ヒビト…》
Hibito!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
しょうげき
うう…なんだ 今の衝撃｡
What was that shock wave?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
くず
悪い ダミアン｡岩が崩れたんだ｡
またすぐ登るよ｡
Sorry, Damian.
There was a loose rock.
I'll climb back up real fast.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
ヒ ヒビト…背中を見せろ…｡
H-Hibito...
Let me see your back.
クソッ！
Crap!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
なんだよ ダミアン｡
What's wrong, Damian?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
酸素のメインタンクが…➡
Your main oxygen tank
破損してる‼
has been punctured!
《予備タンクに
切り替わってる！》
I'm running on my backup tank...
ざんりょう
《メインタンク酸素残量ゼロ…》
My main tank's empty.
My backup tank has...
《予備タンク酸素残量…》
《８０分…》
eighty minutes!
Eighty minutes...
《俺のタンクから
きょうきゅう
酸素を供給できる➡
If only I could give him the oxygen from my tank.
こうぞう
構造になっていればよかったが｡➡
What do we do now, damn it?
どうすりゃいいんだ くそっ…》
しんぞう
《間に合うのか？➡
Do I have enough time?
How much longer will it take Freddy and the rest to arrive?
フレディ達が来るのは
今から え～っと…➡
くそっ 落ち着け》
Damn, stay calm!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
俺は…助からないかもしれない…｡
This might be the end for me.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
やっぱり俺を置いていけ ヒビト｡
You should leave me here, Hibito.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
お前１人なら…なんとか上まで…｡
If you're alone, you can make it up there.
《ダミアン…》
Damian...
《俺がガキの頃 素直に月へ
行きたいって思えたのは…》
As a kid, I dreamed of going to the moon...
《きっとアポロの飛行士たちが
みんな無事に➡
because the Apollo astronauts
all returned alive!
ちゃんと帰ってきたからだ！》
《帰るぞ！》
We're going to make it home!
照明弾が光った位置から
２人が移動していなければ➡
If they haven't moved from the area where the flare was launched,
フレディたちが到着しだい すぐに
ウインチで引き上げられる｡➡
Freddy and Buddy will be able to haul them up, once they arrive.
仲間の救助が来るまで
たいき
待機することが基本だ｡➡
One of their first lessons is to wait for help.
ダミアンたちも
それぐらい わかってるはず｡
Damian and Hibito know that.
(通信:管制官)大丈夫 ２人は必ず
助かるよ｡エディ｡
Don't worry.
They'll be fine, Eddie.
Yeah, thanks for the report.
(エディ)ああ 報告ありがとう｡
りょうかい
了解した｡
Over and out.
(飛行士)エディ｡
Eddie...
Let us pray for their safe return.
いの
２人の無事を祈ろう｡
That's all that we can do.
俺たちに出来るのはそれくらいだ｡
弟 ブライアンの事故の時は➡
When my little brother, Brian, crashed,
ひま
祈る暇さえ なかった｡
I didn't even have the chance to pray.
もう誰も…死ぬことの
ないように｡➡
Let us pray
that no one else
祈ろう｡
has to die.
よし！
Okay.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
待ってろ ダミアン｡
Wait here, Damian.
Awesome... It's working!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
やった…いける！➡
なんとか動かせそうだ｡
I think I can get it running.
It's okay, Damian!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
ＯＫだ ダミアン｡
Let's go.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰの会話
行くぞ｡
Our buggy dropped straight to the bottom of the ravine,
《俺達のバギーが この谷を
まっすぐ落ちたのに対して➡
but Gibson rolled down at an angle.
しゃめん
ギブソンは斜面を横方向に
ゆっくり降りて来ている》
けいしゃ
ゆる
《こいつは傾斜の緩いコースを
知ってるはずだ｡➡
This boy knows which route won't be too steep.
来た道をたどって帰らせる｡
たく
ギブソンに託そう｡➡
We can follow his tracks back.
It's all up to Gibson.
We're going to make it, Damian.
必ず上に戻れるよ ダミアン》
《雑なやり方だけど許せよ》
The ride will be rough, so bear with me.
We can go a little faster.
《スピードを上げていこう➡
I need to get Damian under the sun, to warm him up.
ダミアンを早くひなたに出して
体を温めないと》
《酸素残量 あと４０分！》
Forty minutes of oxygen left.
スリーディー
(原田)星加さん ３Ｄマップ
完成しました｡
Hoshika,
we've completed the 3D map.
(星加)できたか｡
It's finished?
We added a marker to indicate where the flare was launched.
(原田)照明弾の位置にポイントを
つけてあります｡➡
スクリーンにタッチすれば
拡大できます｡
You can zoom in by touching the screen.
すいちょく
照明弾が垂直に飛んだと
仮定すると…｡
If we assume that the flare was launched straight up,
かなり深くまで落ちてるようだな｡
they fell a long way down.
Okay, transmit this data to Houston.
よし！このデータを
ヒューストンにも送信してくれ｡
(原田)はい｡
Yes, sir.
はい｡
Yes.
はい 星加さん｡
来たか！
Yes.
Hoshika...
He's here?
むった
日々人君とダミアンが この谷に
落ちて２時間近く経ったが➡
It's been two hours since Hibito and Damian fell into the ravine,
いまだに通信は途絶えたままだ｡➡
and there's been no word from them since.
今 フレディ船長とバディが➡
At the moment, Captain Freddy and Buddy are on their way in the Beetle.
ビートルで現場に
向かってるところだ｡
(星加)だが到着まで
まだ５０分はかかる｡
But they won't arrive for another fifty minutes.
どうした？六太くん｡
What is it, Mutta?
星加さん ヒューストンに
頼めませんか？
Hoshika...
Can you relay a message to Houston?
何を？
What?
Can you ask them to have Buddy, in the Beetle,
バディたちのビートルの
行き先を➡
head toward this direction?
もっとこっちの方に
こう
変更してもらえないか｡
But, Nanba...
(職員)でも南波君 その位置じゃ
２人が落ちた位置から➡
That's almost twenty kilometers from where they fell.
２０キロくらい離れているよ｡
なんで そこに？
Why should they head there?
日々人は多分…
じっとしていないからです｡
Hibito is
probably on the move.
２０キロ 離れた所に？
Twenty kilometers away?
こんきょ
(職員)根拠はこれだそうです｡
Here is the basis for their logic.
The slope in this area isn't as steep.
(職員)ここだけ傾斜が緩やかに
なっています｡
In other words, JAXA assumes that the two astronauts will try to climb up here,
要は２人がこの緩やかな場所から
谷を登ろうとしていると➡
仮定してビートルを
こっちへ向かわせては➡
and recommends that we send Beetle over.
ジャクサ
というＪＡＸＡからの一案です｡
ダメだ｡➡
No,
they're more likely to be waiting for help at the accident site.
救助が来るまで落下した現場で
待機している可能性の方が高い｡
ビートルは そのまま
バギーの落下地点に向かわせろ｡
Have the Beetle maintain its course toward the point where the buggy fell.
星加さん｡
Hoshika...
No luck, huh?
ダメか…｡
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#42 Hibito's Choice
＜酸素残量 あと２０分＞
Twenty minutes of oxygen left.
I-It's over...
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)＜ダ… ダメだ｡寒い＞
I'm so cold.
Damn...
＜くそっ こいつのスピードじゃ➡
In this thing, it'll take twenty minutes to catch Hibito!
ヒビト達のとこまで
２０分以上 かかっちまう｡➡
We won't make it in time!
それじゃ 間に合わねえ！＞
If I have to die, I'd rather go back to the ravine
＜どうせ死ぬんなら
また あの谷に落っこちて➡
and look up at the stars.
満天の星でも見ながらが いいな｡
そうするか＞
Might as well.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Hibito's Choice"
Hibito...
＜日々人 俺は心配してねえから
祈らねえ＞
I'm not worried,
so I won't pray.
This Week's Space Photo
パンパカパーン！
Soyuz Capsule
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
うひょ～！
Whee!